<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The bloudy booke, or, The tragicall and desperate end of Sir Iohn Fites (alias) Fitz</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105621</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841348</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5924</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5924)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 835:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The bloudy booke, or, The tragicall and desperate end of Sir Iohn Fites (alias) Fitz</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Roberts] for Francys Burton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A report of murders and a suicide.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-A1, F4).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fitz, John, --  Sir, d. 1605 --  Death and burial --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Bloudy booke.</hi> OR, The Tragicall and deſperate end of Sir <hi>Iohn Fites</hi> (alias) <hi>Fitz.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of three men outside a house, one in night clothes kneeling with his hand over his heart, one in night clothing standing holding a sword with its blade pushed right through his torso, and one fully dressed lying dead on the ground with his hat beside him.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for Francys Burton.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:2"/>
            <head>A Narration of the <hi>Bloudy Mvrthers commytted by</hi> the handes of Sir Iohn Fites <hi>(alias)</hi> Fitz, a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhire <hi>Knight,</hi> vpon two ſeuerall Men: and laſtly, to make vp the Tragedy, vpon himſelfe alſo, at <hi>Twick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> nine Myles from London, vpon the ſeuenth day of Auguſt laſt, 1605.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N Wiſtocke, a verie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient place in Deuon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, diſtant from Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth ſome tenne miles, dwelt a worſhipfull Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, called Maiſter Fites, who hauing longe time beene married without anie children, had at length, for a bleſſing to his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Sonne: whome after he had brought vppe in lavdable rudimentes, as well beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a careful father, as if his aged yeares hadde ſeene the hope of his owne poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, hee perfourmed the courſe of Nature, leauing large poſseſsions to his young heir, (being as yet in his Minoritie) of whom the world hoped nothing but a fruitful ripenes, of ſo towardlie a ſpringal, his comelineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5924:3"/>of perſonage increaſing with his yeares, and his deſcretion with his perſonage: he was in his nonage a Ward vnto ſir Arthur Gorge, a worſh. knight. He took to wife the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſir Wil. Courtney, a man grac'ſt with all perfection of an honorable mind. A man louing his countrey, and for his worthie ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, iuſtly beloued of his country: neither did this his faire daughter degenerate from the auncient ſtocke of her father, of whoſe praiſe (ſince vertue chieflie commendeth it ſelfe) I cannot ſufficiently ſpeake, neither in ſetting forth of it, can I bee deemed partiall, ſince her deſerts exceed the meaſure of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie: for as ſhe was a modeſt maiden, ſo being married ſhe gaue euident proofes of a vertuous wife. But her young husbande ſir John (although not then knighted) little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding the happines of ſo rare a bedfellow, followed ſuch errors as youth councelled, &amp; follie led him into; truth it is, if his actions had beene equally agreeable to his perſon, or his guiftes of mind, as plentifullie beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, as the naturall lineamentes of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, he hadde beene the compleate mirrour
<pb facs="tcp:5924:3"/>of an accompliſht Gentleman.</p>
            <p>But it is commonly ſeene, where God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueth vs with more ſpecial tokens of fauor, weby our owne proneſſe to vicious iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, deface his Image, and euermore indeuor to pollute his benefits with our wicked tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion; jt was well ſaid;</p>
            <q>
               <l>turpibus ac prauis imitandis</l>
               <l>dociles omnes ſumus,</l>
            </q>
            <p>This was too trulie verified in ſir Io. Fites, who a while after fell into the careleſſe race of a diſſolute life, and althogh by the often inſtigation of his tender harted wife, he was many times withdrawne from ſundrie temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations of lewd retainers, yet hadd not the countenance of his better friends, and their friendly perſwaſion counſailed him, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he had fallen into misfortune, ere miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune had been ready for his fall. Manye friends and wel-willers he hadde, whoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count might of right challenge the rancke of gentilitie and reputation.</p>
            <p>Amongſt manie, to (whom in the links of perfect friendſhippe, he was ingaged) one gentleman moſt eſpeciallie in all rightes of
<pb facs="tcp:5924:4"/>loue and reguarde, tendered him, (and as it ſeemed) was as much of him againe reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, his name was maiſter Slanning, a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Eſquire and a proper Gentleman, of goodlie liuing, and deſerued credite, of whom moſt men could but ſpeake wel, ſince of almen he was generalie reputed wiſe and courteous. This Gentleman euer inwardlie affected Sir John Fites, ſo that the Countrie noted them (for firme and mutual loue) to be vnfained friends, and ſo indeed they wer, vntil miſhap (euer fatal to ſir Iohn his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings) croſsed their affectionat aſsociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with this miſchance.</p>
            <p>Meeting on a time at Taueſtocke (neere which S. Iohn dwelt) at dinner with manie of their neighbors and friends, with great va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rietie of merriments, and diſcourſe, they out ſtript the noon-tide: Amongeſt other their table talk, S. Iohn was vanting his free Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure in holding his land, boaſting that hee held not a foot of any but the Queen in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland; to whome maiſter Slanning replied, that although of courteſie it were neglected yet of dewe and common righte, hee was
<pb facs="tcp:5924:4"/>to pay him ſo much by the yeere for ſome ſmall Land held of him, the rent beeing by reaſon of friendſhip long time intermitted. Vpon which wordes, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> (grounding his occaſion vpon choller, and heating that choller with diſdaine and pride) told him with a great oath, hee lyed: &amp; withall, gaue fuell to his rage, and reines of ſpight, to the vniuſtnes of his anger, offering to ſtab him.</p>
            <p>But Maiſter <hi>Slanning,</hi> who was known to be a man of no leſſe courage, and more cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, with a great knife that hee had, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the hazard of ſuch threatnings, vppon which grew both multiplication of wordes, and increaſe of hatred on both ſides; vntill by the fayre mediation of theyr friends the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſent, they were accorded to a fained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation: ſo that in briefe, after a while, Maiſter <hi>Slanning</hi> priuately with his man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted homewards.</p>
            <p>Long had he not ridden, but commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his man to walke downe his horſes in the way, himſelfe the whiles taking the greene fieldes for his more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented walke, looking backe, hee might beholde Sir <hi>Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:5924:5"/>Fites</hi> with foure more galloping amaine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. Which ſight, as it coulde not but breede doubtfull and fearefull ſuſpition, ſo could it not but bee a great amazement to Maiſter <hi>Slanning,</hi> who little thought on the deſperate plot of ſo vicious a minded blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucker.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> no ſooner drewe neere him, but Maiſter <hi>Slanning</hi> aſſuring himſelfe of his purpoſed malice, and moſt malicious drift, asked him the occaſion of his comming: to whom Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> (in the rude language of ſcorne and wrath) made aunſwer, he would now reuenge himſelfe for his diſgrace, and ſo at once they fell all vpon him, who with as determinate a reſolution defended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, beeing indeed a man of an vndaunted ſpirit. And ſeeing before his face ſhame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, and hope of lifes ſecuritie, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſperate, he with as bold ſtomacke as a wounded dying man, ſtoode vppon the guarde of his owne ableneſſe, vvhiles Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> beeing prickt on by the bloody vrging of one <hi>Croſſe</hi> his man, grewe to be handned in his butchery: ſo that one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming behind
<pb facs="tcp:5924:5"/>Maiſter <hi>Slanning</hi> with a blowe, (guided by the hand of a villaines hart) ſtrooke him on the head, who falling and ſtaggering back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, was by Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> run through the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, leauing his liueleſſe carkaſſe a monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of terrors, to affright the guiltie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of vnmercifull homicides: but as the one is haſtning to the graue, ſo is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making preparation for flight to eſcape death, not ſhame.</p>
            <p>Great was the lamentation that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try made for the death of ſo beloued a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman as Maiſter <hi>Slanning</hi> was. As for Sir <hi>Iohn.</hi> hee ſoone got himſelfe away, leauing the fulmouth'd report of infamous rumour, to rumour abroade, the report of ſo infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous a deed: but as for his wife &amp; mother, (vertuous Gentlewomen) the torment of theyr ſorrow, is eaſier to be imagined then felt: who in the anguiſh of theyr greefes did pennance for his raſhneſſe, and in the zeale of theyr prayers, laboured for his harty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition.</p>
            <p>Hee for the ſpace of a yere, or neere there about liued in Fraunce, of whoſe carriage
<pb facs="tcp:5924:6"/>there, it is to bee coniectured that it was no otherwiſe then indifferent, yet can I not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him in this his exile for a penitent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertite, howſoeuer the worlde generally deemed the beſt: But in his abſence, the good Gentlewoman led a widdowed lyfe, and by as many means as the procurement of her woorthy freendes could effect, or her owne induſtry labour, ſhee got ſome hope of a promiſed pardon, vpon which after a twelue monthes abſence Syr <hi>Iohn</hi> returned home, with a ſeeming likelihoode of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſorrow for his former miſdeede, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing outwardly euident promiſes of new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and amendement, as ſeeming a mortified man for his treſpaſſe paſt, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring farre better hopes to come.</p>
            <p>In thys meane tyme he had procur'd for his more quiet content, at leaſt a repriuall, if not a pardon, but with thys prouiſo, of his good behauiour euer after. There awhile he lyued welcommed of all, curteous to all, and therefore of all welbeloued: but as it is commonly ſeene, a man naturally hardned in ill, can hardly amende his deformity of
<pb facs="tcp:5924:6"/>wickednes, with cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of diſſembling pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended gloſſe, ſo afterward chaunced with thys man, who in continuance of tyme, did not onely proceed in vnlawful courſes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, but would oftentimes glory in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer execrable fact, &amp; beeing now in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner preſt, in the high-way of all abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he began to roote his thoughts to plot nothing but miſchiefe, inſomuch as firſt, he by little and little lothed his lawful bed, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his pleaſures to lawleſſe deſires, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could the ſweete remembrance of his wiues earneſt affection, with draw him from conſorting himſelfe with looſe prodigals.</p>
            <p>A lamentable ſight it was to ſee a man of his rancke, place, and calling, to be ſo vainly carried away with following the depraued humours of light company: neyther could the intreaty of Freendes, the perſwaſion of his allyes, the counſel of his wel-wiſhers, nor the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſcandall of the world, make him bluſh at his own follyes. Strange it was that a man beeing ſo forewarned, ſhould not be forearmed, for his owne harmes could not make him beware, neyther could the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:5924:7"/>of Gods fauour ſhewed to him, enforce him to conſider the foulenes of his former offences deteſtation, and conforme his after age to a more ſerious meditation of the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite benefites beſtowed vpon him, but the longer hee liued, the worſe he liued.</p>
            <p>At what tyme his excellent Maieſty our King, (after his coronation,) was pleaſed to honor our Engliſh Gentlemen with that auncient rewarde of true deſerts, woorth Knighthoode, it likewiſe pleaſed his royall Grace amongſt many of all Shires through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Realme to inueſt in that order thys Sir <hi>Iohn Fites,</hi> who vnder this title of honor thought to maske his deeds of vice, &amp; vvith the very ſounde of Knight, to boulſter out the community of his ryots: inſomuch as wheras before he was forward he was now both forward, &amp; bold: forward to attempt, bolde to iuſtifie, any vniuſt wrong that his looſe behauiour ſhould vnder goe. Nowe began hee to thinke that the world ſhould wink at his impieties, his credit and knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode was a ſufficient priuiledge. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan hee to entertaine into his ſociety, (as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates)
<pb facs="tcp:5924:7"/>men both of diſſolute &amp; deſperate fortunes, amongſt whom was one (as ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader to the reachleſſe content of his pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered deſires) named co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly <hi>Luſty Iacke,</hi> one whoſe meanes were indeede meane, whoſe good qualities altogether none: but for that as many as knowe him, knowe him without deſcription, the ſequell ſhall teſtifie the honeſty of his conuerſation.</p>
            <p>This luſty Royſter beeing by Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily accepted, and for a more ſpeciall grace that hee had in dooing ill, admitted into his ſociety, ſuncke ſo far into his lyking, as that hee was not himſelfe without this his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion: inſomuch as that Towne of <hi>Taue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke,</hi> though otherwiſe orderly gouerned with ſobriety, &amp; wiſedome of graue Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, was thereby infected, with the beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corruption of drunkenneſſe. Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> by his own inclination apt, and by his retained copeſmates vrged, perſueered the more, to run head-long into ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as vile ſenſuality and pleaſures inclined into, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theyr tyme in riotous ſurfeiting, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyting in abhominable drunkenness being
<pb facs="tcp:5924:8"/>drunke, they blaſpheme and ſweare, and in thys theyr blaſphemy, they teare the diuine name of their almighty Creator into a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand peeces, neyther regarding hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, or dreading feare of damnation, plucking men by night out of theyr bedds, violently breaking windowes, quarrelling vvith Ale-conners, fighting in priuate brab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles amongſt themſelues: all vvhich hazard, (eyther of particuler dangers, or common courſe of Law) could not moue Syr <hi>Iohn</hi> to breake of his diſordered route, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had abuſed the towneſmen, and diſturbed theyr neighbors, Syr <hi>Iohns</hi> ovvn houſe vvas their ſafeſt ſanctuary, or receptacle to cloake theyr out-rages: ſo as it ſeemed, they liued as in tyme of old the common Outlawes of thys Land dyd, neyther worſhypping God nor honouring Prince, but wholy ſubiect to theyr contents alone.</p>
            <p>In ſuch like intollerable courſes of abuſe, beyond vertue, or gentility, did Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with his accomplices, in all his diſorders ſpend his time, little ſtudying to benefite his Country, by being a profitable member of
<pb facs="tcp:5924:8"/>the Common-weale, or little reckoning to be a good ſubiect, by obſeruing the peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtatutes of his Prince, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to increaſe the multitude of his riots, hee ſaid with the Poet,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Cum vino ſumptus cum blandis lauta puellis,</l>
               <l>Menſa placet, baccho prodiga iuncta Venus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wine and women bring moſt men to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, for one is ſo ineuitably awayted by the other, that a royſting drunkard is moſt commonly noted for an incontinent leche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. This was not falſifyed in Sir <hi>Iohn Fites,</hi> who ſo wholy addicted himſelfe to all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable and vicious defamations, that it ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him not (after his diſtemperatures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade) to bring queanes home with him, not eſteeming the precious modeſtie of his vviues bed, and the chaſt deſerts of ſo vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Lady, vvho heereafter may very well ſerue as a rare patterne to all wiues, (that are vnbleſt in hauing ſuch husbands) hovve to carry themſelues with humility, and winke at it with patience. So did this Lady, vntill her vnthankfull husband (glutted in his owne luſt) thought her very preſence to be
<pb facs="tcp:5924:9"/>an obſtacle, and bar to vpbrayd his inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence: for which cauſe (without cauſe) hee beganne to fall into diſlike with her, and at length, would neyther vouchſafe her main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce, or houſe-roome, but with words of diſgrace turned her out of his doores, not leauing her attended by any to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct her.</p>
            <p>In thys plight of diſtreſſe, the vertuous Lady (ſeeing, &amp; by experience hauing had too firme a proofe, of the miſery of ſuch a husband) could not but thinke herſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, howſoeuer indeede ſhee in this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happines was bleſt; for by theſe meanes ſhe auoyded further perrill of death, which hee in his ſteame of wine, had bin likely to haue offred vnto her. In breefe, beeing thus left to her misfortunes, ſhee returned to her worthy Father, who with much ioy, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his diſtreſſed Daughter, with a young daughter of hers alſo: ſo that herein ſhe was moſt fortunate, that ſhe was ſafe, where ſhe might heare of her Knights outrages, but not indure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This Lady beeing by him in this wiſe turn'd away, hee noweknevve himſelfe to be the onely maiſter of himſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:5924:9"/>and might as he thought now be imbolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to follow his own looſnes. Nowe vvas his owne houſe without contradiction, or controlement, open to his aſſociates, where nowe (if they pleaſe) they may erect a little Common-wealth of many iniquities, and much imputation. His purſe they abuſed, his goods they conſumed, and of his perſon they made a ſtale to theyr miſdemeanors: all feard him, few loued him, neither was his worſhippe as much to be reuerenced, as his lewd manners to be abhorred: for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing and inſiſting in his licentious, and odious courſes, not long before his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming towards <hi>London,</hi> being in the heat of his old diſorder, he, (beeing backt by his retainers) fell out with an Officer of the Towne, and after vvith many reprochfull words and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braydings, that he reuiled him withall, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting both himſelfe, the perſon, and the place, hee with many blowes of his dagger. broke his head in ſuch ſort, as the man bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried home, &amp; layd in his bed, it vvas greatly feared, that hee could not eſcape death: which had it hapned, queſtionleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:5924:10"/>it had not onely been a great preiudice, but alſo an indangering to Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> his own life, who after thys deed, was ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the worſt, as that hee little regarding the hatred of his act, ſtoutly perſeuered in the accuſtimation of his former breaches of all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable carriage. But it is euermore notable, that men ouer whom ſinne hath greater predominance, are reſerued for more eſpeciall misfortunes, vntill at laſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouer-ripened, they fall by theyr ovvne rottenneſſe, which on this wiſe happened to Syr <hi>Iohn Fites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maiſter <hi>Slanning</hi> after his death left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him for pledges of Gods bleſsing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him, two ſonnes, and one daughter, his heyre beeing inward to a Knight of that Country of good account and credit, which heyre of Maiſter <hi>Slannings,</hi> beeing come to yeeres of diſcretion, vpon aggreeuaunces of his Fathers death, beeing, (as iuſt reaſon was) loath to ſell his deere Fathers blood, and bearing a minde to reuenge himſelfe by courſe of right, and Law, vpon the but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of his Fathers life: knowing that Syr
<pb facs="tcp:5924:10"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> had but a conditionall and no ſpeciall pardon, (as Syr <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelfe gaue foorth, and falſly blinded the worlde withall) vſed meanes for his attachement, eyther to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure better meanes, or aunſwer the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Iuſtice in that caſe prouided.</p>
            <p>Thys beeing heard of Syr <hi>Iohn,</hi> (who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt his ryots little dreamed on any ſuch incumbrance) it draue him to diuers ſhyfts, but beeing well befreended, (if his carriage had bin ſuch to haue deſerued theyr friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips who indeed were his freends) he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing now no hopes, but ſuch as relay vpon theyr credit, for his better diſcharge vvas driuen to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider better of the vneuen race of his life paſt, aſſuring himſelfe that he was become to the world ſo rediculous, in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo faultie, and of his owne ableneſſe ſo inſufficient to accompliſh his deſires, that if hee could not procure a newe and abſolute Pardon, the old offence of his, being laid to his charge, and his riots ſince, likely to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated by the vulgar knowledge of the whole Country, it would ſurely put, not onely his reputation, but alſo his lyfe in
<pb facs="tcp:5924:11"/>double ieopardy: Theſe reaſons well can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled, feare, not ſhame, made him haſten ſome other courſe to be preſently thought on, and in ſome meaſure to beware of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils to come, though ſcarce repent his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes paſt, <hi>Oderunt peccare mali formidine penae,</hi> doubt of trouble, not hartie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition, pricketh the wicked to auoyde further lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, when as the loue of vertue maketh the vertuous abſtaine from doing euill. So Syr <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſeeing how by his inordinate diſorders he had impaired his eſtate, ſeuer'd himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his wife, wedded himſelfe to wilfull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie, abuſed his neighbours, murthered his freends, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſorted himſelfe with villaines, &amp; cauſed himſelfe to be ſo odious, as his life was now in new danger, he now thought it behooued him to make freends, and to that intent hee poſted toward <hi>London,</hi> where by the way, (continuall Furies tormenting his minde) ere he came to his hopes, he ended his lyfe. For in his iournying towards <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> an accident of great ruth and pitty hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in thys lamentable ſort. Syr <hi>Iohn,</hi> (har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring euen in deſpight of his owne vvill a
<pb facs="tcp:5924:11"/>guilty conſcience in a grieued breaſt) euen as he rode by the way, often ranne ouer the whole courſe of his former euil life: and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer til now did he begin to ballance his own raſhnes, &amp; to conſider the reaſon of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended iourney, which feares of his, nowe doubting leaſt that worthy Gentleman his Father in law, vrged by the wrongs done to his daughter, would not only deny him his befriending fauour, but alſo be a plaintife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his inordinate courſe of life, (though grounded vpon no certainty but the guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his own conceit) he began to fal into a deſperate kind of lunacie, as by the ſequell of his deteſtable deede it plainly appeared. For haſtning towards <hi>London,</hi> he appointed his footeman to meet him by the way, who enquiring as hee went for his Maiſter, met him by hap at <hi>Kingstone</hi> vppon Thames, where he allighted into his Inne, &amp; hauing ſupped (as his order was) hee ſoone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke himſelfe to his bedde: but as a man that hath committed ſome notorious and memorable crime, beeing followed by the Country, flyeth into a large vaſt houſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:5924:12"/>hideth himſelfe, at euery creake of the wind feareth the entrance of ſome ſearcher, or at euery ſtyr of a rat doubteth the attachment of ſome officer, euen ſo Syr <hi>Iohn,</hi> hauing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the crime of murther, and riot, and flying into the ſanctuary of a diſperſed and moleſted mind, was amidſt his quiet follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and affrighted, by the officers of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, guilt, and terror. In his dreames he muttered fearefull wordes, grieuous ſighes, &amp; deep-fetcht grones: moſt fearefull were his viſions, and ſo terrible vnto him, that where hee lay in reſt hee ſuddainly ſtart vp, and called for his horſes, intending to poſt preſently away, for that as he ſaid, Sir <hi>VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Courtney,</hi> with a number in his company were at hand to apprehend him, neyther could they of the houſe perſwade him to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. Moreouer, ſo ſtrange &amp; dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full was his owne minde vnto him, that hee would not ſtay, euer-more crying, that Syr <hi>VVilliam</hi> was at hand to apprehend him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as his gelding being brought him, in the dead tyme of night riding through the Towne, hee met the watch in the ſtreetes,
<pb facs="tcp:5924:12"/>at the ſight of whome he cryed alowd, they were come, they were come: but the watch being by his man more certainlie informed of this his ſo ſodaine malladie, aſſured him that they were not ſir William, but the nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghbors of the towne; adding withall, that he need not doubt, for Sir William was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comming, nor meante to followe him: with whoſe admonitions beeing ſomewhat for the time quallified (not perſwaded) hee rode ouer Kingſton Bridge, towardes Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; but in the waie betweene Kingſton &amp; Twicknam, after hee had ſtraied vppon the Heath a long while, at laſt hee came vnto a Gentlemans houſe, which ſtood ſomewhat out of the waie, and there he knocked, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that as they were gentlemen, they wold reſpect a Gentleman, and helpe him to ſom lodging, and vſed ſuch wordes to perſwade therevnto, as that thoſe of the houſe (the time of the night conſidered) thought him to haue either had ſome other companie, entending to rob the houſe, or elſe to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeene in drinke, or ſome ſuch matter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that loath they were to trouble the
<pb facs="tcp:5924:13"/>houſe with ſuch a gueſt, and ſo ſent him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as he came, directing him vnto the next towne. When as trauailing vp and down a long time, ſomtimes in the waie, ſomtime out of the waie; at laſte hee attained about two of the clocke after midnight, vnto a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Village, called <hi>Twicknam,</hi> ſom two miles from Kingſton (the towne from whence he laſte came) and there by chance, oh cruell chance! hapned to light vppon the ſigne of the <hi>Anchor,</hi> (feare and terrour of his conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience ſuffring him to paſſe no further:) the maiſters name of that houſe, being called <hi>Daniell Alley,</hi> where he cauſed his footman to knocke and beate, and knocked himſelfe alſo vntill ſuch time that he had awaked the goodman of the houſe, who beeing awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, roſe vnto the window and demanded who vvas there? Sir Iohn Fight aunſwered, Here is a Gentleman, and I want lodging; therefore I pray you open the dore and let me in. The Hoſt of the houſe replyed, that he was but a poore man, and kept no Inne, but only a victualling houſe, and that his lodging was verie ſlender to entertain ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:5924:13"/>a Gentleman of ſort, as he tooke him to be. But the Gentleman ſir John Fight anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the worſt bed that was would ſerue his turne at that time, and that he coulde be content to lie any where. The good-man of the houſe, in meere comiſeration of his caſe pittieng him, and in tender compaſsion of his preſent eſtate regarding him, opened the doore, let him into the houſe, ſet up his gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, cauſed his wife to ariſe, and lay a clean paire of ſheets vpon their owne bed, and a clean pilow, her ſelf going to bed in another room, with her mayd and children. Novv as ſoon as ſir John came into the houſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any farther adoe, hee ſent his footeman at that time of the night (being vnacquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Way) vnto London, and tolde him that there hee would ſtaye vntill his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. His footeman being wearie, would-faine lodge there alſo, but hauing no lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and no man being vp at any other Inn, he was conſtrained to departe, and ſo hee tooke on his waie to Brainford, wher he lay that night.</p>
            <p>Sir Iohn, his gelding ſet vp, the dores ſhut
<pb facs="tcp:5924:14"/>in, himſelfe gone to bed, his footman depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with money in his purſſe for his expence and all thinges (as it ſeemed) well, but that the hoſt and his wife obſerued a certain wild and ſtearne looke in his countenance, at laſt being in bedde, called and knocked for the Hoaſt of the houſe to come vnto him, who being come into the chamber (for the good man himſelfe had no place to go to bed in) ſir Iohn ſaid vnto him, I pray thee mine hoſt ſit by me a while: I will, ſaid the goodman, and ſo fetching his cloake to wrappe about him, returned and ſate downe by his bedde ſide. But the Gentlemans mind being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, he could by no meanes ſleepe, or take any reſt, but (oftentimes ſtarting verie ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlie as if he had been ſcard) alwaies hee would be talking of ſome ydle matter or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vttering much diſiointed talke; as tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the goodman of the houſe, that he had lyen in a better bed than that was, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore man replyed, in the pleasingſt ſpeaches that he could (becauſe hee noted him to looke ſomewhat wildly) I make no queſtion thereof sir, but ſurelie I haue no
<pb facs="tcp:5924:14"/>better at this time, (the bed being ſufficient for an honeſt Man) If I had better your wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip ſhould haue it, I am ſorrie for your ſake that it is no better. Thus would hee often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpeake vnto him. At another time he ſaide; I am in Minde troubled, I am diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted: Then woulde he turne him from one ſide to the other. Somtimes he woulde ſaie that sir William Courtneys men were com to aprehend him: for the goodmans wife of the houſe lyeng in the next roome, and ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Man named Robert Goddart, who was a day-laborer, and lodged in another room adioyning alſo, heard both his talke and his vnquiet reſt.</p>
            <p>Thus troubled in mind, and oppreſſed, (as by the ſequele ſhall God willing, apear) either with the remorcefull thoughtes of an accuſing conſcience, or with the deſpairing remembrance of his forepaſſed euill life, or with the fearefull appearance of that dread full day of iudgement, when all fleſhe ſhall be called to an account for their deeds don, euerie one to receiue according to that hee hath done, either good or evill; or with the
<pb facs="tcp:5924:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5924:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5924:16"/>threatninges of Sathan, who viſibly (it may be) appeared vnto him, menacing him with eternal damnation for his fourmer wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or with what other dreadfull appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, illuſion, apprehenſion, terror or temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, hee who knoweth all thinges (and none elſe) certainlie knoweth. Thus I ſaie, being diſquieted, the good-man of the houſ remained with him, vntill betweene foure &amp; five of the clocke in the morning; at what time, ſeeing that the morning was faire and he had buſineſſe to goe about, hee lefte the Gentleman alone, betweene ſleepinge and waking (as it were) and ſoftly ſtealing away, becauſe hee woulde not awaken him if hee could chooſe, called vnto good-man God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dart (who laie in the Chamber cloſe by) to ariſe, and ſo went in to his wife and told her; Wife, <hi>I</hi> muſt leaue you with this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for I muſt goe my ſelfe forth to work. Nay, good husband do not ſo, ſaid ſhe; wil you leaue me at home with him alone, and goe forth your ſelf? I pray you do not, for I am afraid of him, methinkes he talks as if he were frantick. Thus did her minde preſage
<pb facs="tcp:5924:16"/>the future miſchance, which preſent after fel out. The good-man anſwered his wife, if I can get another to worke for me, I will ſtay at home. By this time, the labourer good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Goddart was vp and ready, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to go mowe ſome Vetches, and there fore the goodman of the houſe and he went to fill a bottle of drink to take vnto the field; but as they were together filling the bottle, they heard ſomthing giue a iumpe. I think ſaid one of them vnto the other, the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man be either leapt, or fallen out of his bed: which wordes they had no ſooner vttered, but foorth comes Sir John in his ſhirt, with his naked rapyer in his hande, his eies loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if they hadde ſparkled foorth fire; his countenaunce ſo terrible and gaſtly, as that it was of power to haue ſcarred a mann out of his wittes; and his ſtrength ſo force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able (as it ſeemd to them) it was bootles for on or two to withſtand him, (for needs muſt he go whom the diuell driues) the men fear fully gaue back, and he ſlips out at the back dore and ſo towards the gate which led out of the ſtreet into the back-ſide, and beeing gon forth of the gate, the men ſtept into the
<pb facs="tcp:5924:17"/>backſide likewiſe, wher being, ſaid the good man ſoftlie to the other (the preſent ſighte of his naked weapon, cauſing a preſumption of ſuch a matter) God graunt hee haue not murdered my wife and children; and ſome made towards the gate, purposing to ſhutte the gate after him, which he perceiuing, ſud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denly retires (for his feet were ſwift to ſhed bloud) and eſpyeng the man going to ſhut the Gate, deſperately cried out: Ah villain? Art thou one of them that ſhould aprehend me? Art thou he that ſhoulde laie holde of me? I will ſurely kil thee (ſwearing a blodie oath, if there were no more Men liuing) &amp; therewith ſuddenly and violentlie ran at the goodman of the houſe with his Rapier, but feare made the man nimble and ſwift, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir Iohn could retyre, the goodmanne had cloſed the gate, and his Rapier point hit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting in a little hole of the gate (a fatal hole it was) thruſt him quite through the bodie, be tweene his ſhoulder and his breaſt, ſo that the man fell downe preſentlie and died, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with a woful noyſe and hydeous ſhrieck, crying out; I am kild. The other man who
<pb facs="tcp:5924:17"/>was cloſe by him, (but that the gate was ſhut) might wel haue beene ſerued with the ſame ſawce likewiſe: wherefore being ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into ſuch a terrible feare at the death of the goodman of the houſe as that the ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly knew which waie hee vvent, euen as the fearefull byrd, which hearing the ſounde of the Havkes bels, creepeth into euerie buſh, thereby thinking to eſcape death; euen ſo, I ſaie, he runs vppe and downe, to ſeek ſom place to hide himſelfe, from ſo furious an Enemie. Sir Iohn Fites, being without the gate, runs rounde about by the pale on the ſtreate ſide, ſtill raging and rauing in moſte terrible manner.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of three men outside a house, one in night clothes kneeling with his hand over his heart, one in night clothing standing holding a sword with its blade pushed right through his torso, and one fully dressed lying dead on the ground with his hat beside him.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Thus did he expoſtulate with himſelfe a while, and after this manner did hee deale with himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now a man would iudge that the Deuill himſelfe ſhould be glutted with bloud, but yet, Sir John, (miſerable and wretched man that hee was) takes againe the point of his bloudyed Rapier, and ſetting it ſome twoe or three inches from the ſame place, (what pitty could be expected to bee ſhewed vnto other, from one who would ſhew non vnto himſelfe) with all his mighte, ranne againe thereupon, goring himſelfe quite thorough the body: And yet again, a ſecond time pul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling it out (for Sathans mallice is boundles) (Oh worthie courage, had it been in a good cauſe) he runs into the houſe after the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but his ſtrength fayling him, downe he
<pb facs="tcp:5924:19"/>falles in the floore of the houſe, where hee vvas anon (for as yet fevv had the courage to hinder his attempts, were ſtirring) found wallovving in his owne bloud, like a Pigge that had beene latelie ſticked. Oh heauye ſpectacle! Oh Tragicall and rufull ſighte! Pitty it was, if God had ſo beene pleaſed, that it had not falne out otherwaies.</p>
            <p>NOw tell me, thou that readeſt; Didſt thou euer read a thing more tragical? Didſt thou euer looke vppon a more wofull ſpectacle? Didſt thou euer heare of a more horrible, ſtrange, and lamentable fact? Again, if thou enter into a further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Gods Juſtice, is it not a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warning, to make a man giue himſelfe to prayer vnto the Almighty God of heauen, to bee deliuered from the like temptation? Hereby may a man perceue what the worm of a mans conſcience (of a guilty conſcienſe and the guilt of murder depreſſed with deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration) is. Hereby may al young Gentle men and Gallants, take heed and bee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they giue not themſelues ouer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:5924:20"/>to their luſtes, to follow after and lay holde on the leaſt meanes that may be to do euill, and ſhun ſuch meanes, as might leade them vnto goodneſſe. Hereby may wilde heades perceiue what it is to follow luſte, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and exceſsiue riot, the verie true bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of a diſſolute and vnrulie life, and laſtly (if God call not to repentance) a wicked &amp; vngodly end. Hereby may al Ruffians and ſwearing ſwaggerers (if any ſparke of grace remaine in them) bee warned to leaue off their wicked liues, and to turne vnto the moſt iuſte God, leaſt hee in his iuſtice ſuffer them to be ſo tempted likewiſe. Herby may the Stabbers, and killers of this age, be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ſtaie their hands, and not to ſhedde the bloud of Gods ſaintes (for it is precious in his ſight) otherwiſe hee in his Iuſtice will giue them ouer to be tempted of Sathan, to be the Butchers of their owne ſelues, as this man was. But let me now proceed to make an ende of this wofull and heauye Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Neighbors being by this time gathered togither about the houſe, came in &amp; found
<pb facs="tcp:5924:20"/>the man of the houſe quite dead, hauing yeil ded (no doubt) his ſoule into the handes of his Redeemer. But Sir Iohn Fites not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither dead, but fainting for want of ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth, laie tumbling and wallowing in his own gore, (hauing a ſtrong heart, and myghtie courage, but yet willing (as it ſhould ſeem) to die if he could, vntill that company bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſembled came in, and findinge him in that wofull caſe, tooke him vp, and carried him into the chamber, and preſentlie Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons were ſent for to ſeeke meanes to cure him: but he (as vnwilling now to hear of life as he was before eager of death) woulde by no meanes endure to hear of any Surgeon. But notwithſtanding diuers were ſent for, as namely, maiſter Quinſie of Brainford with others: who being come tented the wounds perforce, but he ſtill pulled them out again, alwaies crying out, that he would die, and not liue. Thus hauing done diuers times, at laſt he was let bloud, and diuers meanes vſed for his recouerie, but all preuailed not, for after he had liued ſome 48. houres after his hurts, he gaue vp the Ghoſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:21"/>
            <p>Vppon the Thurſday after, the Coroner ſate vpon the man of the houſe who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie dead, and by verdict there giuen, ſir Iohn Fites (alias Fitz) was found guilty both of the mans death, and his own alſo, if ſo be he died thereupon. All which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, becauſe hee was a Gentleman borne, and of good kindred, ſo much friendſhippe was ſhewed vnto him, in reſpect of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull ſtocke from whence he deſcended, as that hee was buried in the Chauncell at <hi>Twicknam,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Honourable Earle of Northumber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land hearing hereof, ſent a certaine Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his old acquaintance to commende him vnto him, and alſo to put him in mynd what he had done: how greeuouſlie he had offended his maker, in committing ſo dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable murthers, as alſo in laying vyolente handes vpon himſelfe; and withall perſvva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to repent, and be content to vſe al the beſt meanes that might be for his reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie, &amp; not to continue in his wicked courſ: But all was one with him, he would not liue, but die: only being deſired to aske mercie
<pb facs="tcp:5924:21"/>at Gods hand for his offences, which hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he did; he ſaid that he was ſorrie for the death of the poore man whom ſo deſperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had murdered, and whoſe wife he had ſo greeuouſlie wounded likewiſe, leuing 3. wretched infants vpon the mothers hands. And being asked whether he would wilingly giue any thing vnto the poore woman in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of the loſſe of her husband, hee was contented to beſtowe vpon her an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds. But whither he had any thing in his owne power to giue, that knowe not I. For I think if anie thing be giuen, it muſt proceed from his friends goodwils (and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but ſo it ſhould be) and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>He would oftentimes after he was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, crie out vpon ſir William Courneyes men (whoſe daughter he married) that they were come to apprehend him, and that they would blow him vp with their gunpouder: all which, queſtionleſſe proceeded from the guiltineſſe of his owne conſcience for the wrongs he had doone: and being once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded wherefore he killed the poor man, It was not I, ſaid he, that didde it, but one of
<pb facs="tcp:5924:22"/>my followers, (which thing is note-worthy) He left behind him a daughter, whoſe ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was preſently obtained by an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Earle.</p>
            <p>Thus gaſtly death hauing ſeized vpon his corporall body, we will commit his ſoul (for albeit his ſinnes were great, yet are the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God infinitely greater) into the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the Almighty, (for charitye iudgeth the beſt, and hopeth the beſte) in whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there is nothing but peace.</p>
            <p>In the view of theſe his murthers, there little needeth anye paraphraſe, ſince euerie man that thoroghly conſidereth of the facts themſelues, cannot but in themſelues finde them to be moſt hainous before God, moſt odious before men. This therefore is the report of his deſperat courſes in his life time, who as he cannot be any blot at all vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his vertuous and wel-deſeruing frends, ſo no queſtion he is no more a griefe vnto other, then a fearefull example vnto all his wicked aſſociates.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:22"/>
            <head>Obſeruations ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the former diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>MAny and diuers things are in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent lamentable diſcourſe worthie moſt deepe conſideration, and may ſerue, (the true vſe of all ſuch ſtories) to put vs in mind of our duties towards God, (for we ſhould not read only to know, but learn to know, that thereby we follow the good, and ſhun the euill) the Prince, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and our ſelues. As namely, the eager deſire that Sathan hath to increaſe his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The watchfulneſſe and warineſſe that we ought to haue, that wee come not within his clawes. The wretched eſtate of a deſperate mind. The horror and trembling of a guiltie Conſcience, which purſueth a mans owne ſelfe, when no man elſe doeth. The deſperate courſes of vnbrideled follie. The griefe of friends for ſo hard an hap. The aſtonniſhment of Aſſociates in committing of miſchiefe. The mallice of Sathan, in temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting vnto euill.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5924:23"/>
            <p>The wofull eſtate of two Widdowes, the one in hauing a husband, that was no more comfort vnto her whiles he liued, and yeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo great cauſe of ſorrow being dead: the other, that ſo ſuddenly and vnexſpectedlie, had her deareſt husband (the one half of hir life) by ſuch fatall meanes taken from her. The pittifull eſtate of three Infants left vpon the mothers hands, hauing verie ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to maintaine them. The great libertie that power and might (if God guid not the hart) giueth vnto the performance of euill. The blindneſſe of our ſinfull nature, that wil neuer let vs ſee into our riotous liues, vntill wee bee carried awaie with a full ſtreame of wickedneſſe. The obduracie and hardnes of a mans hart, envred and acuſtomed vnto ſin. How apt to follow the worſer parte, &amp; how hardly framed to good. Drunkenes and fleſhly luſtes, the effects that follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Euill companions, and lewd retainers, the diſcommodities and dangers thereof.</p>
            <p>Our forwarneſſe in purſuing euill, and ſlack<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe vnto good. The manye miſeries that we fall headlong into, for want of due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.
<pb facs="tcp:5924:23"/>The temporall croſſes that god ſendeth vpon his children, to trie their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. What the friendſhip of man is, and how ſoone turned into hate. Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon the Wicked. His loue vnto the godlie. And laſtly (to cloſe vp this diſcourſ) a generall warning vnto all, to put them in mind to amend their wicked liues miſpent, to turne vnto the Lorde whiles they haue time, and to call for mercie, before the gate of mercy be ſhut, that repenting of the euill paſt, they may leade their liues more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, more purely, and more holilie hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: that ſo dying a godlie death, they may make a bleſſed ende. Which that it may ſo be, the Lord of his mercy grant vnto vs all, a ſufficient meaſure of his holy ſpirite, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
